today in the workshop we're working with
waterproof ultrasonic distance sensors
we'll see how these devices work and how
to use them with an arduino we'll also
test them outside and even underwater
we're going the distance today so
welcome to the workshop
[Music]
well hello and welcome to the workshop
and today we are going to be working
with a couple of ultrasonic distance
sensors now of course we've used an
ultrasonic distance sensor before in our
robotics and other projects and we've
used it many times and that's our good
friend the hcsr04
the hdsr04 is a great little sensor it's
relatively accurate it can sense over a
reasonable distance it's very
inexpensive and it's pretty easy to use
however i have an application right now
in which it is not suitable specifically
a robot i'm building that is meant to
operate outdoors and the
hcsr04 is not exactly a great sensor to
use outdoors there are a number of
reasons for that but one of the
principal reasons is that you can't get
it wet so i'm evaluating a couple of
ultrasonic sensors that you can use in a
damp and outdoor environment and i want
to show them to you both today so let's
first of all take a quick look at how
these sensors work and then i'll show
you the sensors that we're going to be
using instead of the hc sr04
ultrasonic sensors use 40 kilohertz
sound pulses to measure distance
these devices consist of a transmitter
and receiver although those can be
combined into one transducer
the transmitter sends out pulses of
ultrasonic sound
if a surface reflects this signal we can
use the time delay between the
transmission and the reception to
calculate the distance
if the distance is shorter the time
delay will be shorter
conversely if it's longer the time delay
will be longer
the
hcsr04 is a very popular ultrasonic
distance sensor it works on 5 volts only
however you can use an
rcwl1601 or a us-100 if you want a 3.3
volt equivalent this sensor can run in a
2-wire or 1-wire mode
it's reasonably accurate and it's very
inexpensive
but the hcsr04 isn't perfect it's not
suitable for outdoor use it's quite
fragile and susceptible to dirt and most
importantly it is not water resistant
however there are ultrasonic distance
sensors that are waterproof and we'll be
looking at two of them today the jsn
sr04t
and the a02 yyuw
let's take a quick look at how these
sensors performance compares to the
hcsr04
the
a02yyuw and the
hcsr04 both have about the same range
the jsn
sr04t however has a longer maximum range
but also a longer minimum range
the accuracy of all of these sensors is
quite good certainly suitable for
robotics and intruder detection
applications none of them however would
be good enough for surveying the jsn
sr04t
and the
a02yyuw can work with both 3.3 and 5
volt logic the hcsr04 however is just a
5 volt device both the jsn sr04t and the
hcsr04
support raw data in other words they
deliver back the length of the received
pulse and leave it to the
microcontroller attached to calculate
the distance the two sensors we are
looking at today support serial data
with serial data the distance is
calculated by the sensor and is descent
as a serial data packet in terms of cost
however both of these sensors are much
more expensive than the hcsr04
however they're not extremely expensive
and if you need a sensor that is rugged
and capable of working outdoors they're
probably good choices
so let's go take a closer look at these
sensors now
now i've got the sensors that we're
going to be using in our experiments
today over here i've also got an
hcsr04 sensor just so you can sort of
compare everything and the one over here
is the a02yyuw
sensor and as you can see it looks a lot
like the
hcsr04 in that it's got a separate
transmit and receive transducer but it
is substantially larger than that unit
now over here in the middle these two
pieces are actually one sensor this is
the jsn
sr04t and it comes as a separate sensor
that plugs into a board over here and
this board is what you um wire
everything up to of course at the
electronics and as you can see the board
is similar in size to the hc
sr04
a little bit taller than it and of
course the sensor is completely
different and it has a fairly long cable
i think that's a couple of meters long
so you can mount it away
and keep your electronics nice and safe
and dry and so these two are the units
that we are going to be using today in
our experiments so let's get going
now the first sensor that we're going to
check out is a jsn
sr04t sensor this is the one that had a
separate circuit board and sensor unit
and another way that this one differs
from the other ultrasonic sensors we've
seen is that the sensor unit just uses
one transducer it's using it as both the
transmitter and the receiver and i
believe that this is the reason why the
minimum range of this sensor is down
around 20 centimeters it just simply
can't flip itself back and forth in time
in order to resolve anything shorter
than that but other than that the sensor
does seem to get a bit of a bad
reputation on the internet and i don't
think it's very deserved quite frankly
there's even a youtube video out there
that specifically tells you not to buy
it and i saw that video after i bought a
couple and thought did i make a big
mistake but what i've noticed about
these videos is that they all use this
sensor in an emulation mode where it
emulates an hcsr04
sensor and there are two aspects about
that first of all i have found by
experimenting that if you change the
timing on it slightly it will work fine
and it's actually within specs of the
hcsr04
another thing i've noticed is that
everyone who tests it tested in this
emulation mode whereas this sensor
actually has six operating modes
including modes in which it calculates
the distance all on its own so i thought
i'd give it a proper test by testing it
in a couple of different modes so let's
go and take a look at this sensor right
now and then i'll show you some code
that we can use to test it in a couple
of different modes and see how it works
the jsn
sr04t
is a separate sensor and printed circuit
board
the sensor is attached to a two meter
cable which attaches to the board with
the two pin connector
the sensor itself is a single transducer
design this transducer acts as both the
transmitter and receiver
the jsn sr04t has six different modes of
operation
in mode 0 which is the default mode this
sensor will emulate an hcsr04
it has the same pin out and can be used
in the same circuits as the hcsr0
mode 1 is activated by shorting the tube
m1 pads in mode 1 the sensor calculates
the distance itself and sends it back as
serial data and it sends its data
constantly
mode 2 is activated by shorting the m2
pads in this mode you need to request
the serial data by sending it the
hexadecimal character 5 5. it will then
return one block of data in this way you
can just request a distance measurement
rather than having it continually sent
to you
modes three through five are activated
by placing a resistor across the mode
pins the value of the resistor will
determine what mode you are in
in mode 3 which uses a 200k resistor the
sensor is an automatic trigger mode this
is like an hcsr04
without a trigger pin the trigger is
fired every 200 milliseconds and you can
read the results and then calculate the
distance yourself
mode 4 which is activated with a 360 k
resistor across the mode pins is the low
power automatic trigger mode it's the
same as mode 3 except the sensor
consumes very little power consuming
only 70 micro amps on idle it does this
by powering down certain sections like
its internal watchdog timer in mode 5
which is activated by placing a 470k
resistor across the mode pads it doesn't
act as a sensor but acts as a 1.5 meter
switch
it will stay high as long as the
distance is less than 1.5 meters
otherwise it will go low this is used
for things like automatic backup
detector alarms
the serial data from the jsn sr04t
is sent at 9600 baud and consists of
four bytes
the first byte is the header and it is
always hexadecimal ff
the next two bytes are the actual sensor
data with the high byte being first and
the low byte being second this is the
distance in millimeters that has been
measured by the sensor
the final byte is a checksum it is the
addition of the previous three bytes
note the checksum only holds the bottom
eight bits of this calculation
upon receiving the data you should
perform the same mathematics and
determine that the checksums match if
they don't then the data has been
scrambled
so now that we know a little bit about
it let's go and hook up our dsn sr04t
now this is the
jsn04t which as we've seen before is a
sensor that comes in actually two parts
there's a sensor unit itself that's on
the cable and a circuit board over here
now if we look at the head of the sensor
itself you can see this is a completely
sealed unit and it just has a transducer
on the front over here there's a little
opening beside the transducer but i
believe it's sealed behind that as well
and that's probably just to allow the
sound to get in a bit better now let's
take a look at the board that comes with
this and if we take a good look at the
board now this is the version 3 board
and the big difference between version 3
and the previous versions is how you set
the mode on version 3 up in the corner
over here you'll see a couple of jumpers
there's one that says m1 a one above it
that says m2 and a couple below that
same mode and the m1 and m2 ones can be
sorted out to put the device into mode
m1 or m2 respectively if you want to go
for some of the other modes you actually
need to put a small surface mount
resistor across this one that says mode
and the value of that resistor will
determine what mode you have if you
don't have anything on it as you see
right now then this is defaulting to
mode 0 which means it emulates an hcsr04
and you will notice the pin outs on the
bottom over here have four pins in fact
if i flip this around so you can see the
writing on that if you can see that
you'll see it says 5 volt trigger echo
and ground and those are indeed the pins
that you use in an
hcsr04 so you can pop this in as a
direct replacement for it if you wish of
course the trigger and echo pins are
also transmit and receive so they can be
used for the other modes as well
but otherwise it's a fairly easy unit to
use it has a really long cable over here
that you can use to separate the sensor
from the board and so this would be
ideal for an application you're using
outdoors
let's say in a vehicle or something
where you have this mounted on the
bumper to detect distance and you have
the circuit board somewhere else within
the vehicle so it's a very inexpensive
and as you're going to see relatively
easy to use sensor
for our first experiment we'll require
an arduino uno
and a jsn
sr04t ultrasonic distance sensor module
we'll begin with this distance sensor
module in its default mode of mode 0.
we start by hooking the ground from the
arduino to the ground pin on the jsn
sr04t
the 5 volt output of our arduino will be
connected to the vcc pin on our
ultrasonic sensor
pin 11 of the arduino will be connected
to the echo or tx pin on the jsn sr04t
and pin 10 from the arduino will be
connected to the remaining pin which is
the trigger or rx pin
and this completes our wiring
now here's a sketch that we're going to
use for the mode 0 demo for the jsn
sr04t
and if you've used the
hcsr04 before you're going to recognize
the sketch because it is virtually
identical
to the sketch that i first demonstrated
the
hcsr04 with in fact there's only one
real difference and it has to do with
timing and i'll show you that in a
moment now we're going to start off the
sketch by defining the connections that
we made to the sensor and then we define
a couple of floats one that represents
the duration the amount of time it takes
the signal to come back and one that we
have to hold the actual distance that
we're calculating and we're going to
bring our distance back in millimeters
and then we go into our setup we set up
our serial monitor over here and we
define our two pins as inputs and
outputs respectively and go into the
loop now the loop again is very simple
this is how we manually use an
hcsr04 and it's how we're going to use
this sensor in mode 0 so we start off by
setting the trigger pin low for 2
microseconds
and then we set it high and here is
where i've changed the timing in the
original sketch that i used for the
hcsr04 i used 10 microsecond pulses and
when you read the spec sheet on the
hcsr04
this is the minimum amount that you can
use but you can use a longer pulse and i
found that with this sensor when i used
a 10 microsecond pulse i occasionally
got intermittent results and i think
this may be the result
of some people saying that this sensor
doesn't work it's simply because i think
they weren't giving it a long enough
pulse so i increased it to 20
microseconds and everything seemed to
work pretty fine so we're going to set
it high for 20 microseconds and then
bring it low and so this will have sent
out our ultrasonic pulses now we're
going to measure the width of the
incoming pulse so we use a pulse in to
measure the amount of time that the
pulse goes high coming in and then we
determine the distance
by that width over here now we're using
343 meters per second as the speed of
sound we're also dividing by a thousand
as we want millimeters so this is what
we're using over here and of course we
have to take the duration by 2 because
the signal is going out and being
reflected back so we only want half of
it and then finally we print our results
to the serial monitor and add a delay
before we repeat this gives everything
time to settle and then we do it all
over again so it's a very simple sketch
let's load it up and take a look at it
in action
and so here we have our mode 0 demo and
as you can see from the serial monitor
it's reading out readings pretty well of
226 millimeters which of course are
wrong
but remember this sensor has a minimum
range of 30 centimeters and that's about
a foot that's about 300 millimeters and
so when it gets below that it'll give a
false reading and i notice with this
particular one that i have that seems to
be the false reading so if i lift the
sensor up a little bit
we should start getting some more
accurate readings and this is the
distance basically between me
and the wall over here so if i get
something in the way
we should start seeing some readings
over here
and now we're approaching that 300
millimeters if i go back a little bit
over here it goes up so the sensor does
indeed seem to work although of course
we're not really accurately measuring
anything right now i don't know if my
millimeters over here is precise
although it's probably in the ballpark
and we will test this a little bit later
for accuracy but at least we know that
our circuit is working and that we are
unable to measure distance with this
ultrasonic sensor albeit distances over
30 centimeters
here's the sketch that we're going to
use for our sensor in mode 1 where it
sends back data in a serial fashion now
we're going to start off by including
the software serial library because the
arduino uno only has one serial port
which is being used for the usb
connection and then we define our
connections to the sensor over here so
the two pins that we've got it connected
to
and we create an array to store the
incoming serial data now if you recall
the data is in a format of four
consecutive bytes so we're going to set
up an array with four elements inside it
and we also need an integer to represent
our distance that's this over here and
we also have a character value to
represent our checksum to make certain
that our data has integrity we'll set up
an object to represent serial port
called my serial and attached it to two
different pins and then go into the
setup in this setup all we do is set up
our serial monitor and also set up our
software serial port at 9600 baud which
is the rate that the sensor gives data
back at
then we go into the loop we check first
of all to see if we actually have data
available if there is we add a small
delay and then we check for the packet
header and the packet header has
hexadecimal ff in it so we look at every
character coming in until we see that
and we know we've got the packet header
once we know we have the header we'll
insert that into the first element of
our array then the remaining three
characters of data will be inserted into
the next three consecutive elements of
the array which as you recall only has
four elements
then we'll compute the checksum by
adding up the data in the first three
elements and seeing the results if that
result equals what we have in the last
element of the array then the checksum
is correct and our data has integrity
and then we'll get the actual distance
and the distance is represented by the
two bytes in the middle of our array
numbers one and number two so we'll put
those two together and print everything
out to the serial monitor and then go
back up and do it all over again so it's
actually a pretty simple sketch let's
load it up and see how it works with our
sensor in mode 1.
and so we're going to repeat the same
test we did on mode 0 with our mode 1
sensor and once again you'll notice that
in idle it is reading about 230
millimeters again the minimum range of
this is 300 so you'll get false readings
when it is at minimum range
lift it up again so that we can actually
get a reading
back to my wall
and i'll put this in front of it move it
and it does indeed seem to be responding
once again we aren't verifying the
accuracy of these measurements just
simply the fact that it does measure
something and we will take it out later
and give it a proper accuracy
demonstration but it does seem to work
in mode one where the sensor itself is
doing all the calculations and just
passing the data back to the
microcontroller
now the a02 yyuw looks a little bit like
the hcsr04
in that you can see that it has both a
separate transmitter and receiver unlike
the last sensor that we just looked at
and it is completely encased in rubber
it's a very nice little unit and i
wanted to see if i could perhaps get
better performance than i did from the
previous sensor using this sensor now
this sensor only operates in a serial
mode it has no emulation mode for the
hcs hcsr04 whatsoever and so we are
going to be using it in that serial mode
now one interesting thing about that
serial mode is that it uses the exact
same data format that our previous
sensor used in mode 1. so we don't even
need to write any new code this time we
can just simply use the last sketch that
we used with this sensor and see how it
compares so let's take a look at the
sensor and then we'll go and see how it
works
the
a02yyuw is a fully waterproof ultrasonic
distance sensor the sensor works on
either 3.3 or 5 volts
it operates on a temperature range of
negative 15 to 60 degrees celsius this
sensor outputs serial data at 9600 baud
and the format of the data is identical
to that of the serial mode of the jsn
sr04t
the sensor has four connections as
follows pin 1 is the vcc which is the
power of either 3.3 or 5 volts pin 2 is
the ground pin 3 is the output selection
if you pull it high or just leave it
alone the data will come back every 300
milliseconds if you bring this pin low
the data will come back every 100
milliseconds the 300 millisecond data is
considered to be more stable so unless
you need data at a rate of 100
milliseconds you should just leave this
pin alone and finally pin 4 is the uart
output which contains the serial data
from the sensor so now let's go hook up
the a02 yyuw sensor
now here's just a quick look at the
a02yyuw and there's not really that much
to look at i've got the sensor over here
and i've also got an adapter cable and i
purchased this from df robot and it's
under their part number
sen0311 and they included this little
adapter cable which adapts the jst
connector on the sensor two four
separate wires that you can use for
experimenting purposes so that's going
to be very handy so let's just take a
quick look at the sensor itself again
really not much to see it's a completely
sealed unit you can see some resemblance
to the
hcsr04 and that has got a separate
transmit and receive transducer sealed
away with two mounting holes on each end
over here if i flip it over to the back
over here you'll see it's also
completely sealed it's got kind of a
rubberized feel to it and it's got a bit
of weight to it it feels like a very
solid product and so i'd feel quite
comfortable mounting this outdoors using
it in my outdoor robot etc so let's go
and hook it up and see what it can do
the wiring for our next sensor is just
as simple as the last one was a gain
will require an arduino uno
and an a02
yyuw ultrasonic sensor unit
we'll begin by connecting the 5 volts in
the arduino to the vcc of the ultrasonic
sensor this is the red wire
the arduino's ground will be connected
to the sensor's ground which is the
black wire
we'll connect pin 11 of our arduino to
the receive or blue wire on the sensor
and the sensor's remaining green wire
which is the transmit lead will be
connected to arduino pin 10
and this completes our wiring
now here i have my a02 yyuw sensor and
once again i'm going to try to measure
distances with it now you can come
closer than 30 millimeters with this one
so i can come in
a little bit more 30 centimeters excuse
me
i can actually come in quite close right
now
and here i am down to about 50
millimeters
and of course i can move it back
and get a reading as we would expect
and so this does seem to work just fine
using the code that we used for the
other sensor and once again we'll have
to actually take it out and give it a
proper test to see how accurate it is
so we've seen how our sensors work but
we haven't really given them a proper
test here on my workbench i just simply
don't have the space to check out their
range and our first sensor wouldn't even
work at anything underneath 22
centimeters and so what we need to do is
bring these things outside and that's
exactly what i'm going to do right now
i'm going to take both sensors outside
give them a test and see how they work
and i'll also even test out their
waterproof capabilities so let's go
ahead and take a look at that so i took
the experiment outside into my tiny
backyard along with a computer and i set
everything up so that i could read the
reflection off of my wall
i measured everything as best that i
could but of course the accuracy of
these measurements is going to be a
little bit off just because of my
measurement process
i then went and took measurements for
both sensors at a number of different
distances i also tried wetting the
sensors and was pleasantly surprised to
see that it really had no effect on the
reading by the way those of you who saw
my video on comparing ir sensors in
ultrasonic may notice that board in the
background unfortunately it was unusable
for these tests
here are the results that i got and as
you can see both sensors were pretty
accurate
2460 millimeters was the furthest that i
could measure in my tiny yard and as you
can see at the one meter mark they're
both very close on i would say that
either of these sensors would work
properly in your application although if
you need distances under 300 millimeters
you're probably best going with the
a02yyuw
as the jsn sr04t will not measure low
distances accurately also another thing
to note was that the ambient temperature
was rather cool it was only 14 degrees
celsius and of course that will affect
the speed of sound i made no effort to
compensate again wetting the sensors
didn't change the readings so i don't
have a separate set of readings for that
but i was pleasantly surprised to see
that because this means that these
sensors will indeed work in an outdoor
environment
now i do most of the filming for the
dronebot workshop channel here in my
workshop but as you saw from the last
scene i've also taken it occasionally
outside we've occasionally run a robot
on the floor outside the room
but there's a lot of my house you
haven't seen yet and there was one area
of my house that i never thought i would
be showing you yet i'm about to show it
to you right now and that is my bathroom
and the reason for that is i want to
give these sensors a test and see if
they will actually work under water and
as i don't own a swimming pool the
largest body of water that i have in my
home is my bathtub now i am not
expecting accurate results i'm not even
sure if i'm expecting any results from
these because of course the speed of
sound in water is different than the
speed of sound and air but i would like
to see if they are actually waterproof
and if they will work underwater so
let's go and take a look and see if they
will so i took the experiment up to the
bathtub and very carefully
immersed the sensors under water i had
to be particularly careful with the a02
yyuw because it has a very short cord
and i didn't want to drag my arduino
into the tub the results however were
very disappointing i got basically the
same reading from both of the sensors at
least each sensor gave a consistent
reading it wasn't the same reading
between the two of them and so they were
completely useless inside the tub
however one thing i did note is when i
pulled them out of the bathtub they
continued to work just fine so immersing
them completely in water didn't affect
them a bit they worked properly when
they were out of the water so they're
indeed waterproof but you can't use them
in a bathtub well that wraps up our look
at outdoor ultrasonic sensors and i hope
that you found it useful i know that i
found it useful because i think i can
determine which sensor i'm going to use
for my outdoor robot project a project
that i will be showing you very soon by
the way here on the dronebot workshop
youtube channel so if you're not a
channel subscriber please do that all
you need to do is click on the little
subscribe button and if you also click
on the bell notification you will get
notified every time that i make a new
video and that of course is assuming
that you've got notifications enabled on
your youtube account now if you need the
code that i used today or if you want a
bit more information about the two
sensors we looked at head over to the
dronebotworkshop.com website where you
will find an article that accompanies
this video and there's a link to that
article right below the video and if
you'd like to discuss this well the best
place of course is the dronebot workshop
forums we've got a lot of great people
on the forum who can help you out with
your projects or you could perhaps help
them out as well it's free to join so
head over to the forum where you will
find a thread that discusses this video
specifically and finally if you want
more information about what's going on
in the workshop or more info about that
outdoor robot please consider
subscribing to my newsletter again it's
absolutely free it's not a sales letter
just my way of occasionally keeping in
touch with you to let you know what's
going on here in the workshop so until
we meet the next time please take good
care of yourself please stay safe out
there and we will see you again very
soon here in the dronebot workshop
goodbye for now
[Music]
you